<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Corner House at UT - Switch Mode Amplifier, Power Electronics</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/switch-mode-amplifier-power-electronics.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2021-12-30T19:11:00-06:00</updated><entry><title>H-Bridge Inverter</title><link href="/h-bridge-inverter.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-12-30T19:11:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-12-30T19:11:00-06:00</updated><author><name>AudiTT</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-12-30:/h-bridge-inverter.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This post details how I chose the MOSFETs and boostrap circuitry(Capacitor and Diode) for my H-Bridge Inverter Design&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I took Power Electronics Laboratory (EE462L/EE394-7) course during Fall 2021 and long story short, I enjoyed it immensely. While dealing with circuits operating at 
few 10s of watts, I never really fussed a lot about efficiency but once that power starts to go up, efficiency becomes paramount (not just to minimize energy wasted 
but that wasted energy often manifests as heat, how do we now dissipate it safely?). In this context I studied and built various circuits for AC-DC rectification 
(Diode Bridge rectifier), DC-DC converter (Buck, Boost and SEPIC) and finally DC-AC inverter (H-Bridge). I already utilized the AC-DC diode bridge rectifier for 
powering my &lt;a href="https://1sand0s.github.io/solder-reflow-oven-20.html"&gt;Solder Reflow Oven 2.0&lt;/a&gt;, so suffice to say that the knowledge I acquired during this 
course has already been put to good use. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most interesting aspects of this course was the H-Bridge Inverter design challenge. The challenge was based on optimizing along two thrusts, the first 
thrust focused on maximizing the efficiency of the inverter and the second thrust was concerned with minimizing the bill of materials (BOM). We were tasked with 
selecting the power MOSFETs which were a part of the phase legs of the inverter and in designing the boostrap circuitry required to provide a floating voltage source 
to drive the high-side MOSFETs in each phase leg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My design achieved the 2nd highest efficiency in the history of the course and I will discuss how I went about modelling the circuit to choose the appropriate components.      &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/HBridgeInverter.png" width="800" height="600" /&gt;
Figure 1 : H-Bridge Inverter board&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt; Table of Contents &lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#Inverter"&gt;What is an Inverter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#MOSSelection"&gt;MOSFET Selection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#Boostrap"&gt;Boostrap Circuit Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#CircuitTesting"&gt;Circuit Testing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#Efficiency"&gt;Efficiency Measurement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What is an Inverter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="Inverter"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An inverter is a device that changes a DC input to an AC output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/1sand0s/H-Bridge-Inverter"&gt;Github Link to the H-Bridge Inverter repository&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Switch Mode Amplifier"></category><category term="Power Electronics"></category></entry></feed>